<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the proceedings of the Parliament &amp; Army; and the resolution of the souldiery: with the remonstrance, grounds, and reasons, of these unexpected changes, and sudden interruptions; the shutting up of the Parliament-House doors, and the absenting of the Members. Also, the mediation and interposing of divers honorable members of the council; and the accord and proposals, to be presented from the general-council of officers.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82225</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D752</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1000_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207841</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866869</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866869</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119157</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82225)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119157)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 148:E1000[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the proceedings of the Parliament &amp; Army; and the resolution of the souldiery: with the remonstrance, grounds, and reasons, of these unexpected changes, and sudden interruptions; the shutting up of the Parliament-House doors, and the absenting of the Members. Also, the mediation and interposing of divers honorable members of the council; and the accord and proposals, to be presented from the general-council of officers.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Emanuel Richardson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octber. 17".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119157:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OF THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE Parliament &amp; Army; AND <hi>The Reſolution of the Souldiery:</hi> WITH The <hi>Remonſtrance, Grounds,</hi> and <hi>Reaſons,</hi> of theſe unexpected Changes, and ſudden Interruptions; the ſhutting up of the Parliament-Houſe Doors, and the Abſenting of the Members.</p>
            <p>Alſo, the <hi>Mediation</hi> and <hi>Interpoſing</hi> of divers Honorable Members of the Council; And the Accord and Propoſals, to be preſented from the General-Council of Officers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Emanuel Richardſon,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119157:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119157:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>DECLARATION</hi> OF The <hi>Proceedings</hi> of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Army.</head>
            <p>WHereas there is aroſe ſome Miſunderſtanding betwixt the Parliament and Army, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the late Repreſentation and Petition of the Officers and Souldiers; wherein was made manifeſt, their Deſires to remove all occaſions of jealouſie and ſurmize, and to fruſtrate the expectations of any, who by blowing up the Coals of Diſſention, hope to warm themſelves thereby: Declaring their faithfulneſs and integrity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the peace and welfare of theſe Nations, and their endeavouring to render themſelves ſerviceable to a well-regulated Commonwealth, wherein the Liberties of the people both ſpiritual and civil may be fully ſecured, and perſons of known integrity, piety, and ability, employed in places of publique truſt and conternment; reſolving to be inſtrumental in bringing forth ſuch a foundation of Government, whereby all the good people of theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may rationally expect that ſuch Liberties &amp; Rights ſhall be preſerved to them and their Poſterities; and that there may be ſuch a ſettlement, as may not be liable at
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119157:3"/>every change of Governours to have the peace thereof di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed, by introducing new Governments.</p>
            <p>And it being judged neceſſary, for the keeping of the Army under ſuch a Conduct as may render the ſame ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the Government of the Commonwealth, a Committee of Nomina ion was deſired, for the electing of Offi<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; and a Commander in Chief was remonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for: But the Parliament was ſo far from condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hereunto, that they paſſed a Bill for the appointing 7 Commiſſioners for the Government of the Army; and voted null the ſeveral Commiſſions of the Lord <hi>Lambert,</hi> Col. <hi>Disborow,</hi> Col. <hi>Berry,</hi> Col. <hi>Kelſey,</hi> Col. <hi>Aſhfield,</hi> Col. <hi>Cobbet,</hi> Col. <hi>Packer,</hi> Col. <hi>Barrow,</hi> and Major <hi>Creed,</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged them from all Military Imployment, diſpoſing of their Regiments to other Officers, and giving them Commiſſions.</p>
            <p>This Reſolve of the Houſe rendered the Members un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviceable Patriots; for moſt of the Officers and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers declared for the Lord <hi>Lambert,</hi> and the aforenamed Colonels, and were commanded to their arms on <hi>Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> Night.</p>
            <p>The like Orders were iſſued to thoſe Regiments that adhered to the Parliament, <hi>viz.</hi> Colonel <hi>Moſs,</hi> and Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Morleys</hi> Foot, who were commanded to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where they kept guard in the Palace-yard, the Court of Wards, and parts adjacent; but late in the Evening the Houſe roſe, being adjourned till the next morning, at which time they were prevented from ſitting: for the Speaker coming in his Coach (according to his uſual manner) was turned back again in <hi>Kings-street,</hi> and not permitted to come to the Houſe; many others alſo were denyed entrance, and received interruption; there being ſtrong Guards mounted in ſeveral parts, and divers Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments placed in <hi>Kingstreet,</hi> and the Abbey; amongſt the reſt, the Lord <hi>Lamberts</hi> Regiment of Foot had the Avant-guard near <hi>Kings-Gate;</hi> and Colonel <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wſon</hi> his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment maintained the Out-guard at the Palace-yard gate,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119157:3"/>and within lay a pa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty of Colonel <hi>Moſſe</hi> his men, and in the Tower ſome of Colonel <hi>Morleys.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe continued within Pike length of each other for many hours, not ſtriking one blow, and very indulgent they were in obſerving their Duty.</p>
            <p>Several Troops of Horſe were alſo drawn up in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and had Orders to rande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouz, proceeding very moderately; not dreading, but contemning all Plots of Treachery. Lofty Actions, and high Reſults; and the World may in time tremble at their Attempts: for the ſouldiery are very unanimous, with whom are joyned ſevenſcore gallant horſe, formerly the Parliaments Life-guard, commanded by Major <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> who was detained in <hi>White-Hall</hi> moſt part of <hi>Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day;</hi> but his Lieutenant, with the reſt of the Officers, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to the Lord <hi>Lambers,</hi> and diſſented even in the firſt Juncture of theſe Interruptions.</p>
            <p>So that the Intereſt of the Parliament many declined, notwithſtanding the endeavours of ſome to promote and carry on the Work in <hi>London,</hi> and to have raiſed the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> and Trained Band of the City; but it proved ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and (contrary to the Citizens Addreſs) their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were fruſtrated: for the Commiſſioners of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> were much divided in their Conſultations at <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> and could not accord to raiſe or put in a poſture their Military Forces, either in an offenſive or defenſive way. Onely thus much they ſeemed to acquieſce in, <hi>To uſe all poſſible means for the interpoſing and begetting a right underſtanding betwixt the Parliament and Army.</hi> The like Orders being ſent to the Commiſſioners in <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark,</hi> and being read and communicated to them at a General Meeting, it was agreed and aſſented to, That the Militia and Trained Bands ſhould be forthwith raiſed, which was done accordingly, and about eight of the clock in the morning 8 gallant Companies appeared in their Arms (conſiſting of one thouſand men) with Yellow-Colours,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119157:4"/>and the Bible, and continued in the Park near St. <hi>Georges</hi> Fields till the Evening; at which time, two of the Lord <hi>Lamberts</hi> Troops of Horſe, and a party of Foot faced them, but in a friendly motion, exchanging onely words, and countermarching to each other without blows.</p>
            <p>In this Intervale and grand Affair, moſt of the Boats about the River of <hi>Thames</hi> were ſeized by the Souldiery, from <hi>London</hi>-Bridge to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and divers ſmall Veſſels man'd, and the Wharfs and Water ſide guarded; till at the laſt, by the in erpoſing of ſome honorable Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Council of State, a Mediation was aſſented to, and Propoſals to be offered by the Council of Officers, in order to the cementing and making up of theſe unhappy breaches.</p>
            <p>And for the better facilitating and carrying on ſo expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient a Work, the reſpective Regiments that were in arms on both ſides, were ordered on <hi>Thurſday</hi> night to repair to their ſeveral Quarters, which accordingly was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: And upon the drawing off of Colonel <hi>Moſſes</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of Foot from <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the Lord <hi>Lambert</hi> took a view of them, riding through their Ranks &amp; Files, who was ſaluted with ſeveral Vollies.</p>
            <p>The next morning, being <hi>Friday,</hi> the Parliament was expected to meet at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> but it proved other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, their Re<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olutions being at that to decline ſitting at preſent: ſo that now the Doors of the Parliament Houſe are ſhut, and a Guard of ſoldiers kept in the Lobby and other places.</p>
            <p>And whereas the people are much amuzed and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented in theſe unſetled Times, at the various Changes and Revolutions, yet it is hoped all things will center in a well regulated Government, for the juſt Rights, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Priviledges of the People. For effectuating wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſeveral Propoſals are to be preſented to the Council by the Council of Officers, together with the Ground
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119157:4"/>and Reaſons of their preſent Tranſactions. In the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim, the Soldiery are united, and proceed in a cordial and affectionate Agreement and Union, for a General: adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the Lord <hi>Lambert,</hi> and other their ſuperiour Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, who have ſincerely profeſſed, That they have no other then faithfulneſs and candor in their hearts and actions towards the people, in order to a true and firm ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of theſe poor diſtempered and diſtracted Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>The General Council of Officers have had ſeveral Meetings at <hi>Wallingford</hi> houſe, in order to their model<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and drawing up of certain particulars touching theſe unexpected Tranſacts: Lieutenant General <hi>Fleetwood</hi> ſits in Council; and 'tis hoped there will be a happy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, and mutual accord, for the preventing of all abuſes, interruptions, and irregularities for the future, and the ſetling of theſe Nations in Peace and Tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
